Today’s דף Daf is ס"ג, Samech Gimmel, 63, and we pick up,
we are now in the fifth and final פרק. Perek. It’s a
significant shift from—I mean, we’re still dealing about the issue about סתם
יינם Stam Yeinam and יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, but a significant shift
from the last פרק, Perek, which was all about how something becomes
סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, what stage is a thing considered to be
wine, primarily also what type of touch—direct, indirect, with intent to touch,
without intent to touch, intent to touch but doing it in a
completely different context for a different reason. Actually, if you think about
it, the actual סוגיות sugyot were not complicated in the last chapter.
Usually, it was like a story: Oh, so-and-so did this and he,
like, you know, an apple fell into a barrel of wine, he
stuck in his hand to grab the apple, they stopped him from
moving his hand, and so and so, and therefore they solved the
problem. Okay, that’s like was what—but then of course the big questions
of the last chapter was, wait, wait, what’s the principle here? Like,
you know, is it because he wasn’t intending, is it because of
this, how is it different than that case? And you had these
huge תוספות Tosafot that were trying to not only figure out the
principles, but also really discuss practical applications and all of the ways
in which they dealt with those types of issues in his time.
In this last פרק, Perek, the focus certainly at the beginning is
the issue about being משתכר באיסורי הנאה, mistaker be'issurei hana'ah, making a—being
hired, making not a profit off of, being paid for work regarding
things that are forbidden in benefit, and therefore being paid for work
in working with the יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. And then in the
end, we’re going to get back to actually stuff that will be
more reminiscent of some of the earlier סוגיות, sugyot, which are more
כשרות Kashrut related and about wine that gets mixed up with other
things and questions about תערובת, ta'arovet, mixtures, and so on. Some classic
סוגיה sugya learned in when people are learning כשרות Kashrut come at
the end of this פרק Perek at the end of the מסכת.
Masechet. But the מסכת Masechet began with the basic statement that you
are—that if a Jewish worker is hired by a non-Jew to work
with יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, okay, and the גמרא Gemara gets to
סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, okay, he cannot use the payment, he cannot
use the money that he has been paid. That money is forbidden
in benefit. So he’s not allowed to be hired out, which we
learned in an earlier משנה, Mishnah, which was the discussion about being
paid to, you know, stomp the grapes with the non-Jew and the
question is at what time did it become wine? So the—and here
it’s basically saying that if he is paid, that that money is
forbidden, is forbidden in benefit. The
גמרא Gemara so asks the question, well why is this true? Is
this a general principle about איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah that you can’t
get paid to work in them? Because you’re not actually directly benefiting
from the object itself. And I should mention to you that more
than once have I been asked the question about, let’s say, can
I be a waiter at a non-kosher restaurant where not only do
they serve non-kosher meat, big deal, that’s not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah,
but they actually will serve dishes of בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, which
is forbidden in benefit. Okay, can I, you know, work at a
soup kitchen where it’s בשר בחלב? basar bechalav? That’s maybe easier because
you’re not getting paid for it. Is that considered being paid for
something that is forbidden in benefit? Because you’re not getting הנאה hana'ah
from the thing, you’re being paid to serve it.
So the גמרא Gemara says that actually as a general rule that’s
not a problem by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. It gives an example
by ערלה Orlah or שמיטה, Shemitah, though שמיטה Shemitah is not איסורי
הנאה, issurei hana'ah, that not only is that not a problem, but
if you actually sell something that’s אסור בהנאה—I assur behana'ah sold my
בשר בחלב basar bechalav and I got paid, so I did my
עבירה aveirah was in the act of selling it because I sold
it and I got money, and that’s being—getting benefit from, like either
I used it in some way to get physical benefit from or
I sold it and I got money, that was considered getting benefit
from איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. But now that I’ve done that, the
money itself is not forbidden in benefit and I can go ahead
and use the money. There’s an interesting question of הכי תוספות hachi
Tosafot am I לכתחילה lechatchilah allowed to use the money and so
on, but we’ll bracket that. Okay, and that’s even when it was
money paid for איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah where you could say it
is any use of that money is indirectly benefiting from the object
itself. And even there, בדיעבד bedi'avad it’s not a problem. So certainly
if I’m working in a טרף treif restaurant and they’re paying me,
I’m not getting benefit from the בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, that’s okay.
Okay, so that can’t be why it’s a problem with סתם יינם,
Stam Yeinam, with יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. So the גמרא Gemara therefore
moves on and says, okay, maybe it’s a function of this idea
that it’s תופס את דמיו, tofes et damav, okay, that when you
basically
as opposed to the case of בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, if I
go ahead and I sell you my little עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
and you pay— for it, then the money I get is also
forbidden in benefit, right? And if I use that money to buy
something else the thing I bought is forbidden in benefit. The status
of forbidden in benefit transfers to the money, okay? So those are
two different principles, right? Because שמיטה Shmita for example is in the
תופס את דמיו tofes et damav category, but not in the איסור
הנאה issur hana'ah category, right? So you have איסור הנאה issur hana'ah
which is something like well יין נסך yayin nesech and בשר בחלב,
basar bechalav, and
then you have תופס את דמיו, tofes et damav, which is that
the status transfers to the money, which is again יין נסך yayin
nesech and עבודה זרה avoda zara and let's say I don't know
שביעית. shevi'it. Okay? So, the point is איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, if
you're talking about בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, yeah go ahead, be a
waiter at a non-kosher restaurant, get paid for it, you're not really
benefiting from the בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, and the money that you
get or whatever once you got that money, continuing to use it
is not considered getting benefit.
Why not benefit from the בשר בחלב basar bechalav you're a waiter?
Because you're being paid to serve the dish, you're not getting direct
benefit from the physical object. Okay. So, תופס את דמיו, tofes et
damav, okay, that would explain that's true, that now that applies to
other things, so if you sold your שביעית shevi'it or you sold
your יין נסך yayin nesech and you got money, that money let's
say by יין נסך yayin nesech that money is forbidden. But here,
again, you didn't sell it, okay? You just got paid to work
with it. That is not money for the actual יין נסך. yayin
nesech. And the גמרא Gemara proves by שביעית shevi'it that if you
get paid to work with שביעית, shevi'it, your salary is not שביעית.
shevi'it. The איסור issur of תופס את דמיו tofes et damav is
only money paid for the object, not your salary. So from perspective
of this being paid a salary it should be okay and from
perspective of that being paid a salary it should be okay. Okay?
And nevertheless the משנה mishna says you can't get paid a salary
for יין נסך yayin nesech and the basic answer is חומרא דעבודה
זרה. chumra de'avoda zara. Okay? You're right, it doesn't fit either category,
but it's important to know that, okay? Because you will get
the I've definitely gotten these questions about working with meat and milk
and so on. Okay, but because of the issue of עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, although a salary does not fit into this category and
does not fit into this category, you're not allowed to it does
we do apply it by עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And then the
גמרא's Gemara question was, what about what about in terms of סתם
יינם? stam yeinam? And the conclusion was, yes, we apply it by
סתם יינם stam yeinam as well. Okay, so by סתם יינם stam
yeinam and יין נסך, yayin nesech, don't get paid a salary for
working with them, and if you do, the money is forbidden. Okay,
but that's a special הלכה halacha of סתם יינם. stam yeinam.
If you own a supermarket then you can't even be stocking the
stuff because then you're getting...
right, I mean if you own a supermarket or a liquor store,
actually that's where I think I got my most recent question was
somebody wanted to know if they could work in a liquor store
which had non-kosher wine in it. So that actually is interesting
because they're not, now I have to rethink that answer a little
bit. Would that fall into logically, you're saying,
it's an interesting question. They're not... owning the liquor store would obviously
be a problem. Then you're actually getting money for it and it's
all those issues. But that's an interesting question if being a guy
who just stocks the store etc. Yeah how is it maybe it's
not different from our משנה? mishna?
My question is, that's an interesting question. Is it like... I have
to think about that one. That's actually an interesting question. Okay, thank
you for mentioning liquor store. Okay, so anyway, so now we so
that was a basic summary of yesterday but I wanted to review
it. And now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Let's take a look. I know this was covered yesterday, but
since I'm just getting back in, I was away for a few
days, I want to review it. So we're going to start, we'll
go quickly, but we'll start from the bottom of ס"ב עמוד ב'.
Samech-Beis Amud Beis. דבי רב ינאי. Debei Rav Yanai. About 10 lines
from the bottom, right, near where the asterisk is.
אתנן זונה? etnan zona?
Yeah. So we're going to start again. דבי רב ינאי יזפי פירות
שביעית מעניים. Debei Rav Yanai yazpi peirot shevi'it mei'aniyim. So since we're
talking about שמיטה, Shmita, okay, and what
constitutes the exchange of something that the status transfers as opposed to
being paid a salary where the status doesn't transfer. So דבי רב
ינאי יזפי פירות שביעית. Debei Rav Yanai yazpi peirot shevi'it. So they
and presumably, I'm guessing they did this to be nice to the
עניים. aniyim. So here Michael's an עני, ani, he's been he's been
going around and picking all of the Jaffa oranges in people's orchards
on שמיטה, Shmita, and he's got these boxes of oranges. And the
only problem is is that it's going to be in a month
the time of ביעור biur is going to be up and he's
not going to be able to eat from it anymore, although there
are no oranges...
What?
There are no oranges then.
There were no oranges then. Fine, whatever.
Anyway. So what I do is I say Michal, do you you
know what, I mean my sense is, the bar doesn't say this,
but my sense is that this was why it was done because
it mentions עניים. Aniyim. Okay. Lend me 20 crates of oranges, okay,
and then I'll go ahead, I'm I'm wealthy, I'll distribute it to
my workers, okay, and and I'll I'll use them all up in
the next month, and I'll get around to paying you back after
שמיטה, Shmita, and I'll give you 20 crates of oranges which aren't—which
don't have קדושת שמיטה, Kedushat Shmita, and then you'll be able to
use it. So, great little deal, okay? So. How much did he
pay back?
But money would be fruit, right?
Yeah, well, right. But let's assume it was with fruit, which raises
a which raises a ריבית Ribbis question, because you're not supposed to
borrow objects that are going to be used up and pay back.
It's like because the the the value might change. Let's let's not
let's skip that as well, let's skip that as well, also raises
interesting questions, right, which is why שמיטה Shmita at the end of
the year isn't—is it מבטל mevatel the loan? Ha! How about that
question? Okay, anyway, maybe we're at a פרוזבול. Pruzbul.
Maybe we're at a פרוזבול. Pruzbul. Anyway, okay, ופרעו לו בשמינית. U'pru
lo b'shminis. Anyway, they paid it back on on the eighth year.
אתו אמרו ליה לרבי יוחנן. Atu amru leh l'Rabbi Yochanan. They said
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, how can they do this? Because they
thought that the fruit that was paid back with should be considered
like חליפי שביעית, chalifei Shvi'is, like when you bought money with and
שביעית Shvi'is produce with money and the קדושה Kedusha should transfer. And
the obvious difference is is that it's not exchanged at the time.
I I pay Michael back here after that fruit has already been
eaten up. So normally the idea of the status transferring is when
you have both objects and an exchange is happening at the same
time and the קדושה Kedusha transfers, although the קדושה Kedusha already always
remains on the product itself, but it extends to the exchange. Anyway,
here here not. So I mean that's the issue. So they went
and said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and he said, יאות הן
עבדין, Ya'ot hen ovdin, they're doing properly, okay. וכנגדן באתנן מותר. U'knegdan
b'etnan mutar. And I'll give you an example of this where it's
not considered an exchange for the status to apply to something if
it's not at the same time, like in a case of an
אתנן, etnan, a gift given—a gift—a payment given to a prostitute. When
is that payment given that it would be considered to be actually,
you know, the payment to have this forbidden status to use in
the המקדש? Hamikdash? Now there's an obvious difference, right? Because you could
say that, look, here the fruit doesn't get the the transferred status,
the extended status, unless the other fruit is present at the same
time, because it's going from the original fruit and extending to the
new fruit. So they have to sort of be one exchange for
the other and at the same time, and certainly the original oranges
can't be eaten up when I give him the other fruit. What's
there to transfer then or to to extend? Whereas the payment to
a prostitute, even after services are rendered, then you get your bill
and you pay it, and then that should have that status, because
that's money paid for that service and it should get that status.
Okay, but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, even in that case,
even though it was payment for services rendered, it's not considered an
אתנן etnan unless somehow that object was around at the time that
the services were being rendered, okay. Let's take a look.
But it was around, it just wasn't offered in payment.
Or well, that's what I mean. It wasn't being given in payment
at that time. Okay, so but yeah, thank you. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, וכנגדן באתנן מותר, u'knegdan b'etnan mutar, if that
was the same thing by an אתנן etnan that payment was made
later, it would not get a status of an אתנן. etnan. דתניא,
D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, נתן לה ולא בא עליה,
natan lah v'lo ba aleha, if he first paid—gave her the the
the money or let's say it's a sheep, it's a question of
using it for a קרבן, korban, and without and you know and
and at the time he gave it he hasn't yet had intercourse.
או בא עליה ולא נתן לה, O ba aleha v'lo natan lah,
or he had intercourse but he didn't give her the sheep. אתננה
מותר. Etnanah mutar. The אתנן etnan is permissible. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, wait a minute. נתן לה ולא בא עליה פשיטא. Natan
lah v'lo ba aleha pshita. You know, the last case that he
gave her it but he hasn't had intercourse, or the first case,
excuse me, that's obvious, you know, if there's no—if there's been no
services yet, obviously it's not going to have a status. כיון דלא
בא עליה מתנה בעלמא הוא דיהב לה, Keivan d'lo ba aleha matana
b'alma hu d'yahav lah, since he hasn't had intercourse, it's only a
gift. וסו V'su and and the last case, בא עליה ולא נתן
לה, ba aleha v'lo natan lah, had intercourse without giving it, הא
לא יהב לה מידי, ha lo yahav lah midi, he didn't give
her anything! So what is there to be an אתנן? etnan? So
this whole ברייתא Braisa doesn't make any sense. וכיון דלא נתן לה
מאי אתננה מותר? V'keivan d'lo natan lah mai etnanah mutar? How can
you say the אתנן etnan is מותר? mutar? Nothing's been given yet.
אלא הכי קאמר, Ella hachi ka'amar, this is how you have to
read it. נתן לה ואחר כך בא עליה. Natan lah v'achar kach
ba aleha. It doesn't mean it never happened. It means it didn't
happen simultaneously. First the payment was given and then the they had
the act of intercourse. או בא עליה ואחר כך נתן לה. O
ba aleha v'achar kach natan lah. Or there was first the act
of intercourse and then the payment was given. אתננה מותר. Etnanah mutar.
It's permissible. Which is like crazy! Like the only time it's an
אתנן etnan is if like it was given exactly at the same
time. So how do you even define—what does it mean?
Does he mean that like maybe 10 days later or...?
No, yes, that's what פשט pshat he's—what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
saying. If it was given a day later, if you had the
story of יהודה ותמר Yehuda v'Tamar and he came a day—you know,
a day later, a week later, or whatever it was, and he
paid it, it's not—even though it's payment for services rendered. Since it's
not at the time of the act, it's not a status of
אתנן. esnan. Which seems a little crazy.
Okay, what's even crazier is that the אתנן esnan is forbidden, but
the actual prostitution no-
That's a separate question, right? Whether, you know, the nature... I mean,
there's an איסור issur of לא יהיה קדשה מבני ישראל. lo yihye
kadesha mibnei Yisrael. No, it's saying it's...
it was frowned on, but it's not an actual...
It might be forbidden, it might be an עבירה aveira of לא
תעשה, lo ta'aseh, לא תהיה קדשה מבנות ישראל. lo tihiye kadesha mibnot
Yisrael. That's just not our discussion right now. Okay, נתן לה ואחר
כך בא עליה. natan lah v'achar kach ba'aleha.
So now the גמרא Gemara wants, okay, if that's פשט pshat of
this ברייתא, braita, let's figure it out. נתן לה ואחר כך בא
עליה, natan lah v'achar kach ba'aleha, first it was payment and then
they had the act of intercourse. כי בא עליה, ki ba'aleha, if
he gave her the sheep, he said, here's this sheep if you,
you know, מה תתני לי אם תבוא אלי, mah titteni li im
tavo elai, is that the פסוק pasuk by תמר? Tamar? Right? So,
oh, here's this sheep. And then they had the... and so she
had the sheep, and then they had the act of intercourse. So
okay, at that moment, the sheep should get that status, it's sitting
around in her house for this act and it should be defined
by it. ליהוי לאיסור אתנן למפרע? lehavei l'issur esnan lemafrei'a? Let it
retroactively be defined as אתנן. esnan. Presumably if they never finished the
deal, he'd be able to take it back. You're giving it in
payment and you gotta get the services, and when it happened, let
it have that status. So אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, said
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, כשקדמה והקריבתו. kshekiddma v'hikrivato. Oh,
she went and she brought it as a קרבן korban before the
services were rendered. Okay, so... exactly. Maybe it's מכפר mechaper already. She
figured get in your תשובה teshuvah early before the עבירה. aveira. היכי
דמי? heichi dami? Now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, what's the case?
One minute, let's figure this out. So she brought it as a
קרבן korban and then the services were rendered, so it wasn't an
אתנן esnan because the act hadn't been finalized yet. So wait, what's
the case? אי דאמר לה קני לך מעכשיו, i d'amar lah kni
lach me'achshav, if he says that when after we actually, you know,
have intercourse, retroactively, or actually maybe even not retroactively. He basically says,
you know, own it as of today. Here's the sheep, it's now
yours. פשיטא דשרי, peshita d'sharei, then obviously it's permissible, דליתא בשעת ביאה,
d'leisa b'sh'at bi'a, ומתנה בעלמא הוא דיהיב לה. u'matana b'alma hu d'yahiv
lah. It's not around when they have intercourse because she brought it
as a sacrifice and it was only a gift. I know... I
know this... this system. So I think what the גמרא Gemara is
saying, and we'll see the final answer, is that קני לך מעכשיו
kni lach me'achshav means and I won't have a right to claim
it back if we don't finish the deal. Okay. So if that's
true... in that unlikely case... right, but we want to contrast it
to the case... so that case, obviously it wouldn't be an אתנן.
esnan. ואי דלא אמר לה קני לך מעכשיו, v'i d'lo amar lah
kni lach me'achshav, and if he just said you won't own it
until the act is final... so היכי מצי מקריבא? heichi matzi makriva?
How could she have brought it as a קרבן? korban? It would
be... you can bring it, but how is it going to be
kosher? Forget that it's an אתנן, esnan, it's not hers! ואיש כי
יקדיש את ביתו קודש אמר רחמנא. v'ish ki yakdish et beito kodesh
amar Rachmana. מה ביתו ברשותו אף כל ברשותו. mah beito b'reshuto af
kol b'reshuto.
Okay, she has to be in her
possession, or in her ownership. אלא דאמר לה ליהוי גבייך עד שעת
ביאה, ela d'amar lah lehavei gabaich ad sh'at bi'a, let it be
with you until we have the act of intercourse, ואי איצטריך לך
קני מעכשיו. v'i itzterich lach kni me'achshav. But if you need it,
you can take possession as of now. Okay, but presumably it's still
going to be for payment. All right. So it's a little funny
that it framed it that way, because what it could have said
is you will own it as of now retroactively once we have
ביאה. bi'a. Okay. But anyway, that might have been what the גמרא
Gemara was referring to before, but I'm not going to worry about
that exact case yet. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So in that case, okay, says that that's פשט pshat and therefore
it still is good. Because since she didn't own it... because excuse
me, because since she was able to take possession of it and
to own it now before the act of intercourse had occurred, it
wasn't defined and she was considered a full owner before that act
was occurred, it wasn't defined as what do you call it, as
an אתנן. esnan. Okay. So now again, what's a little bit funny
about all of this is that you would think that the גמרא
Gemara would want to talk about a more interesting middle case, which
is that basically
if the act is done, retroactively you own it as of now.
And then she goes ahead and she brings it. Right, that case
I think would be interesting because that case you could say they
finished the act, so they did the act on Thursday, he gave
it to her on Monday, so retroactively she owned it as of
Monday, but it wasn't... so and that way it should have been
hers and it should have been an אתנן esnan because it was
payment, retroactively we see it was payment, but at the time it
was
brought, the retroactive hadn't happened yet. You know, so like that would
have been like an interesting question that the גמרא Gemara is not
fully unpacking. But the basic short version is that the גמרא Gemara
says is that if she owned it outright, right, at the time
when it was given, then obviously it would not be an אתנן.
esnan. Okay, it has to be that she doesn't own it until
the act takes place. And only if it's given to her and
it says it'll be final when the act takes place, then it
would be an אתנן. esnan. But it's a little unclear is let's
say he says when the act takes place it'll be owned retroactively,
but, you know, that's a little unclear which of those two cases
that the גמרא Gemara was discussing would that fall into. Okay, but
anyway that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan statement. An אתנן esnan doesn't work
if it was given first and it was finalized first, and it
doesn't work if the acts were rendered and then it was given
either, which is bizarre because then it was given in payment, and
it only acts if it was given and then it became final
when the services were rendered.
If we didn't say anything, you know, unless they say, 'Alright, well,
you know, I want to contract you out,' and she says 'Alright
fine, you know, your payment will be the equivalent of this אתנן,'
esnan, okay fine, the sheep is worth that. If we didn't say
anything, קונה, koneh, you know, so it would seem there would be
a problem, right?
Well, that's what I'm sort of saying that it would seem to
me that if we bracket the, you know, if we don't have
the scenario of that she brought it before the act was final
and so on, it would seem to me that the, that a
normal case, which it was paid upfront and then the services were
rendered, and once that was true, then retroactively she owned it from
the time that it was paid, to me it would seem that
that would be an אתנן, esnan, but that's not being spelled out
explicitly. Okay. בעי רב הושעיא. baei Rav Hoshaia. רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaia
asked. קדמה והקדישתה מהו? kidmah vehikdishasoh mahu? Okay, now let's say in
the scenario you said, where he said, 'Look, I'm going to pay
you money, it's ממש mamash יהודה ותמר Yehuda veTamar case, but,' and
then you'll give it back to me, it's now really there just
as a type of a collateral,
but, alright, is that what the גמרא Gemara said? No, actually, I'm
sorry, I'm making it complicated. You, you don't own it now, you'll
own it when the act is done, but if you need it,
you can take possession earlier. Okay, and then it said that if
she did that and brought it as a קרבן, korban, it's כשר.
kasher. So he says, let's say she didn't yet bring it as
a קרבן, korban, with that scenario. He says, 'Here it is, you'll
own it when we, when we do the act, but if you
need it, you'll own it'... you can take possession earlier. And she
went ahead and she sanctified it before they did the act. מהו?
mahu? What's the story? Is that considered like she took possession of
it and it's now out of the אתנן esnan category, but she
didn't bring it yet as a קרבן. korban. כיון דאמר מר, keivan
de'amar mar, since we teach אמירתו לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט, amirato lagavoah kimesirato
lahedyot,
that when you sanctify something to God, it's like you handed it
over to another person, it is like taking of possession, the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash takes possession, so כמאן דאקריבתה דמי, keman de'akrivasoh dami,
it's like she actually brought it as a sacrifice, which means then
he said, 'If you need it earlier, you can take possession,' and
in that case where she acts on that, it doesn't become an
אתנן esnan because then she fully owns it before the act took
place. So when she sanctifies it, is that like before they did
the act, is that like she took possession now and she fully
owns it before the act and therefore, right, it's not in the
category of אתנן? esnan? That's one possibility. או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say, השתא מיהא קאי ואיתא בעיניה, hashta miha kai ve'isa
be'einayah, that's not considered taking possession. If it's still around, even though
she sanctified it, she hasn't really used it yet, okay, and therefore,
since it's still physically present when they have the act of intercourse,
it does get defined as an
אתנן. esnan. ותפשט ליה מדרבי אליעזר, u'tifshot lei mid'Rabbi Eliezer, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. One minute, why don't you infer it from
the, from the way רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer explained the ברייתא? braisa?
דאמר רבי אליעזר, d'amar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, שקדמתה
והקריבתה, shekadmosoh vehikrivasoh, when does it save it from a status of
an אתנן? esnan? When it was brought as a sacrifice before the
act was done. So דוקא, davka, it sounds like he gave that
case, דוקא הקריבתה, davka hikrivasoh, only if it was brought as a
sacrifice, אבל הקדישתה, aval hikdishasoh, if she only had sanctified it, that
wouldn't save it as an אתנן, esnan, then it would be physically
present when they had the intercourse and it would get the status.
So the fact that he jumped to the case of offering it
as a sacrifice sounds like anything less would still have a status
of an אתנן. esnan. לא, רבי אליעזר גופא קמיבעיא ליה. lo, Rabbi
Eliezer gufa kamiba'ia lei. He wants to know what's פשט, pshat, why
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer jumped to the case of sacrifice. מאי? mai?
What should we say? מי פשיטא ליה לרבי אליעזר דהקריבתה דוקא? mi
pshita lei l'Rabbi Eliezer dehikrivasoh davka? Did he say, 'No, the only
way it would save it from a status of an אתנן esnan
is if she actually brought it as a sacrifice before, okay, that
it no longer existed.' אבל הקדישתה לא? aval hikdishasoh lo? But if
she only sanctified it, even if she had already taken possession and
so on, but it was around when they were having the intercourse,
that'll give it its status. דאיתא בשעת ביאה, de'isa besha'as biah, if
it's around when they're having intercourse, that gives it the status. או
דילמא, o dilma, or, and that's why he jumped to the case
that she offered it as a sacrifice. או דילמא, o dilma, or
should we say הקריבתה פשיטא ליה? hikrivasoh pshita lei? It's obvious to
him if it was a sacrifice it saves it as an אתנן,
esnan, it was out of the picture before they had intercourse. והקדישתה
מספקא ליה? vehikdishasoh mesapka lei? If she sanctified it, he didn't know
what to say about that. So the fact... yes, he did leapfrog
over the case of her sanctifying it, but is that because it's
obvious to him that that case it is, it is an אתנן,
esnan, or because he doesn't know what the הלכה halacha is in
that
case? תיקו, teiku, so we don't have an answer to that. But
again, I find all of this a little bit strange because what's
not I think spelled out enough is this question about is it
retroactive? If you think about it, here she is, she sanctifies it,
okay, he says 'If you need it you can use it earlier,'
she sanctifies it, so presumably that's satisfied. satisfies his condition of if
you need it you can use it earlier. She used it, she
sanctified it, so it belongs to הקדש Hekdesh and then they go
ahead and they have intercourse and the animal is still around, so
now what happens? An animal that's already been sanctified becomes an אתנן?
Esnan? Like, how does that work? Like, do we, you know what
I'm saying? It's like, once it's already קדוש Kadosh and owned by
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, now it can become an אתנן? Esnan?
So or is it that no, once they've had intercourse retroactively we
see that it was an אתנן Esnan from the very beginning and
when she sanctified it it was an אתנן. Esnan. So the question
of like at what stage is this status happening, you know, and
is it retroactive or not, is not fully spelled out yet.
Yeah, this seems very academic and you know, but it seems totally
to negate the spirit of this. You know what I mean? Like
we have like, אשר תשכב עם בהמה, Asher tishkav im behemah,
all those kind of things, or we don't want to see אותו
היא, oso hi, like let's say he had sex with the animal.
You kill the animal too, but also this is the שור shore
that so-and-so's getting killed over. So the same thing, oh, this is
very animal-ish
one that they...
it's very nice, but what...
yes, it's true, there's obviously a bigger moral message here, but what
הלכה halacha does is הלכה halacha comes and quantifies exactly what are
the types of things that fall into this legal category that's communicating
this broader message that you're saying is if it's got a broader
message we should interpret it in a more expansive way rather than
more... exactly, בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, it seems to be... I hear
that, okay, but that doesn't mean that technically it's פסול. pasul. Okay,
but anyway, so what this is being, what Rabbi Yochanan is saying
is that it actually has to be the animal has to sort
of be, you know, in her possession and the sort of the
transfer take effect, you know, when they're having intercourse. Or even if
the transfer, she owned it earlier, at least the animal still has
to be around when they're having intercourse so that its status is
defined through that act of intercourse. Okay, that's fine. But then he
says, but if first services were rendered and then the payment was
made, then it's not, which seems very strange, right? It's clearly being
given in payment, but he says no, somehow it is, you know,
I guess this is the analogy, like when you swap פירות שביעית,
peiros shvi'is, the קדושה kedusha of the קדוש kadosh object here, the
normal one here, and because they're both here at the same time
the sanctity transfers. Somehow it is if you would the stigma of
the act, this seems to be how he's looking at it. The
stigma of the error, you know, the analogy, the stigma of that
act as it when as it, you know, which is being performed,
defiles, you know, that animal, that sacrifice. So if that animal is
there and it's in her possession and she's taken possession or the
ownership was finalized, then stigmatized by the act. But if the, you
know, but if she owns it free and clear beforehand, it's out
of the picture. Or if the animal is paid after, even though
it's being paid for the act, since it wasn't there and present
in the context when the act was being done, it doesn't get
that status. Okay, so now the גמרא... Gemara...
this should be bearing in modern הלכה?
halacha? Well, גמרא Gemara had it have bearing for פירות שביעית peiros
shvi'is by the analogy.
No, but with money today. Can it be used for charity or
for...
yeah, that's a separate conversation about what types of funds like, you
know, should not be accepted, you know, yeah, whatever, but that's a
בבא קמא bava kama discussion. Okay. Now, בעל ואחר כך נתן לה
אתנן מותר. ba'al ve'achar kach nasan lah esnan mutar.
If first it was the act and then it was the money
it's permissible, and that was the comparison to the פירות שביעית. peiros
shvi'is. Okay, so which is again what our whole focus on, remember
about borrowing the Jaffa oranges and paying it back after. רמיני, Ramini,
I'll ask you on this. בעל ואחר כך נתן לה. Ba'al ve'achar
kach nasan lah. We have a ברייתא beraisa that pretty much says
the exact opposite. Okay, first he had intercourse and then he gave
it to her, אפילו מכאן עד שלוש שנים, afilu mikan ad shalosh
shanim, even three years later, אתנן אסור, esnan assur, it's forbidden. Okay,
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so that's
a pretty explicit contradiction to your Rabbi Yochanan's whole claim, and this
is actually makes a lot of sense. So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק אמר רבי חייא לא קשיא, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar
Rabbi Chiya lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאמר היבעלי לי בטלה
זה, Ha de-amar hibali li bitla zeh, הא דאמר לה היבעלי בטלה
סתם. Ha de-amar lah hibali bitla stam.
If you say have intercourse with me and I'll give you this
sheep, okay, then even though she didn't own it yet, but then
when it since the sheep was around and identified when the act
was being done and in the end it is used as payment
for that act, it has become stigmatized by that act. But if,
you know, after the act, it had not been identified, the sheep
was around, it was with my whole, you know, pen full of
sheep or whatever, okay, but it was not identified, then at the
moment of that act, right, there this particular sheep was not special
and therefore was not stigmatized by that act, even though it was
given in payment later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וכי אמר
לה בטלה זה מאי הוי? ve-chi amar lah bitla zeh mai havi?
But who cares if he says this sheep? הא מחוסר משיכה. Ha
mechusar meshicha. She doesn't own it yet. Now I tried to exactly
say, okay, like I tried to find a middle ground. She doesn't
own it, but it's been identified and in the end it's been
given as payment, and that's enough for it to be stigmatized by
the act. But the גמרא Gemara isn't happy. The גמרא Gemara thinks
that within Rabbi Yochanan, you know, based on we framed it earlier
as well, you need her act actually to have been payment at
the moment the act was being done. So so what if
it's
identified? For it to be a problem it has to be payment
at the moment. So the גמרא Gemara says בזונה עבודת כוכבים be-zona
avodat kokhavim דלא קניא במשיכה de-lo kanya bi-meshikhah so
it's actually a non-Jewish prostitute and therefore they don't they don't need
to take possession of the object to own it. Usually we could
say a non-Jew takes possession by payment of money, but here where
it's not actually no money is being paid for the sheep, services
are being given for the sheep, so the giving of the services
is like the paying of the money. So as soon as the
services are rendered, she now owns the sheep exactly at that moment.
Okay, so that's how it works for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So
even though the sheep is given, the way the ברייתא braitah would
be read, given three years later, since the possession was transferred at
the moment of the intercourse, it has that status. Again, not פשט
pshat of the ברייתא braitah at all. פשט pshat of the ברייתא
braitah is that even though the transfer occurs later,
but the גמרא's Gemara
reading it no,
the handing over occurred later, the transfer only if they identify a
specific sheep. Right, the transfer, exactly, yeah, because if the transfer occurred
at the moment. So the גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא ve-iba'it eima
maybe
this sheep is
too old three years later. Exactly. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you
want, you can say לעולם בזונה ישראלית le'olam be-zona yisre'elit it was
a Jewish prostitute וכגון דקיימא בחצרה. u-khgon de-kayya ba-hatzeirah. But you know
how the transfer happened at the time of the act? Because the
sheep was in her front yard, so she was קונה koneh with
קנין חצר kinyan chatzer once the act was completed. So the גמרא
Gemara or was okay ואי דקיימא בחצרה ve-ee de-kayya ba-hatzeirah if it's
in her yard בעלה ואכנסה לה ba'alakh ve-akhnesun lah what do you
mean that it was given later? It wasn't given later. At the
moment the act was complete it was given, not only was possession
transferred, it didn't have to be delivered, it was already in her
yard. הא קניא לה ha kanya lah she already owns it. It's
in her yard. So you can't even read the ברייתא. braitah. The
ברייתא braitah says it was delivered it was delivered three years later.
לא צריכא lo tzerikha you need it for the case דשוויה ניהלה
אפותיקי de-shavya niela apotiki that okay, fine fine fine. It wasn't that
she that possession was transferred at the moment. What happened was, he
said, this will be your liens will be not collateral, your liens
for the money I'll owe you will be, you know, centralized in
this sheep, specifically about this sheep. Okay, דאמר לה de-amar lah he
said to her אם אייתינא לך זוזי im ayisina lakh zuzei this
really is now like the יהודה ותמר Yehuda and Tamar story. Okay,
if I bring you money later, although there it was bringing the
sheep later. Okay, if I bring you money later מכאן עד יום
פלוני mi-kan ad yom ploni anytime between now and the end of
the month so מוטב mutav then good, I'll pay you and then
don't take the sheep. ואי לא ve-ilo but if I don't, you
know, you know, you know,
it's a what does it you know 30-day payment period or whatever,
if I don't pay you by the end of the month שקלי
באתננך shakli be-etnanekh then you can take the sheep. And therefore, since
when that sheep so that means the sheep was delivered three years
later, okay, but since she had a lien on that particular sheep,
then that then
retrospectively it's like she always it had always owned it, or there
was enough ownership at the time of the act that it defined
its status. So now what we have saying is for רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, okay, we could have maybe lived in some I think
interesting middle position, that if the sheep is identified even though there's
no yet technical rights to it, if it's identified and given in
the end that's enough to give it its status. But the גמרא
Gemara wants רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it only has the status if
she takes possession and it's around at the time that the services
were rendered. So this ברייתא braitah that says it was delivered later
is a special case where she had an אפותיקי, apotiki, she had
rights and, you know, property rights to that sheep even at the
moment that the services were rendered although they weren't exercised until payment
was not made. Yes.
Apoteken in Spanish is a mortgage. Oh really?
Interesting.
Probably comes from Greek or Latin or something. Yeah. Okay, okay, fine.
So now we got the whole אתנן etnan thing figured out although
of course רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan argument is not at all פשט
pshat in the ברייתא braitah and is a little hard to get
our head around and any of us would normally think if payment
is made later that's its definition, but that's his position. Okay and
now we're going to sort of continue to play it out and
this is going to be very relevant for other issues like שבת
Shabbos issues as you'll see, or כשרות kashrus issues. Let's take a
look. מתיב רב ששת mative Rav Sheshet רב ששת Rav Sheshet asked
about trying to so narrowly define when is this get the status
of the thing that is being paid for. אמר אדם לחמוריו ופועליו
amar adam le-hamorov u-fo'alav a person says to his donkey drivers and
his workers לכו ואכלו בדינר זה lekhu ve-ikhlu be-dinar zeh לכו ושתו
בדינר זה. lishtu u-sheteu be-dinar zeh. Here, you know, you worked for
part of the job is with benefits, I pay for your lunch.
Okay, it's lunchtime, everybody here's a ten dollar coupon or here's ten
dollars a person, go and have take your lunch break. Okay, ואינו
חושש ve-eino hoshesh and he doesn't have to be concerned that you
know what they're going to do? They're going to take this money
and they're going to go to the nearest McDonald's. That's not his
business. Okay, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say McDonald's. It says McDonald's.
אינו חושש ולא משום שביעית, eino choshesh lo mishum shevi'is, they'll go
use this money and they'll buy שמיטה Shemitah produce, okay, and and
you know they'll and they'll use it. What's the matter? You're allowed
to eat שמיטה Shemitah produce, but they'll buy it from somebody who
actually is is doing business with שמיטה Shemitah produce, which you're not
allowed to do. Okay, ולא משום מעשר, velo mishum ma'aser, this is
closer to my McDonald's case. He doesn't have to be concerned that
they'll go ahead and buy it from עמי הארץ, Amei Ha'aretz, you
know, it doesn't have תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros taken from it and
they'll eat fruit and they'll eat stuff that is not kosher, doesn't
have תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros taken. Isn't there some kosher McDonald's? What?
There's such thing as some kosher McDonald's. Okay, thank you.
ולא משום יין נסך, velo mishum yayin nesech, and he doesn't have
to be concerned that you know that let's say they're non-Jews, okay,
and he's going to they're going to go and let's they're going
to go ahead and well even if they're Jews whatever we're talking.
Anyway, they're going to go ahead and they're going to buy יין
נסך yayin nesech from and and then it will be like he
got הנאה hana'ah from יין נסך yayin nesech because even if it's
a non-Jew buying from a non-Jew, I give it to my non-Jewish
worker, they go to a local non-Jewish wine seller and buy it,
why is that my problem? Non-Jews are allowed to drink that wine.
But maybe the problem is, you see I was trying to a
little bit too much jump... I know, I know, I know, it's
יין נסך. yayin nesech. I was trying too much to jump to
a question so I get, I get, I actually have gotten questions
like this. Can I go ahead and give my you know can
I go ahead and a poor person on the street you know
who's asking for money and I don't like giving him money, can
I walk in a store with him and say order what you
want and I'll pay for it. Is it like and let's say
he orders something that's בשר בחלב, basar b'chalav, is it like I
am getting הנאה hana'ah from the בשר בחלב, basar b'chalav, I like
I bought the בשר בחלב basar b'chalav and gave it to him,
or is it like is it like... well I but I'm using
it to do whatever... but there's still issues about when you do
even give something as a gift there's elements of הנאה hana'ah there.
Let's just bracket that for a moment. Anyway, is it like I
bought the בשר בחלב basar b'chalav and gave it to him? Or
he just bought it and I'm just paying his bill, right? Okay,
or questions like this. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara though, its more
initial issue, so I ran a little bit too much to thinking
about that scenario. The גמרא's Gemara more initial issue is forget this
person you know well is that it's not just the עבירה aveirah
that my workers are
going to eat non-kosher food. The concern is that is it like
I am feeding them non-kosher food? Not just like a type of
לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. I'm not right, so if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, okay רש"י Rashi says like this. He says let's look
at just רש"י Rashi לא משום שביעית. lo mishum shevi'is. He says
שמא יקחו בו פירות שביעית מן החשוד למוכרן ותניא במסכת סוכה אין
מוסרין דמי פירות שביעית לעם הארץ יותר מג' סעודות. shema yikchu bo
peiros shevi'is min hachashud lemochran vetanya b'maseches Sukkah ein mosrin d'mei peiros
shevi'is l'am ha'aretz yoser mi'gimel se'udos. So it's like I am now
giving my workers שמיטה Shemitah produce and I'm not allowed to give
שמיטה Shemitah produce to
somebody who won't eat it properly.
Or ולא משום
מעשר,
velo
mishum
ma'aser, דעמי הארץ
הם ויקחו שאינו מעושר ונמצא זה מאכילו.
d'amei
ha'aretz
heim v'yikchu she'eino me'usar venimtza zeh ma'achilo. It's like I am feeding
them. It's not a type of לפני עיוור lifnei iver which is
why if it was לפני עיוור lifnei iver right it's not just
oh they're going to go ahead and use the money and eat
non-kosher food. That's like not my business, I just gave them money.
But the concern is no, maybe we should דווקא davka reframe it
as since that you are you told them
you're feeding them lunch and you gave them the money, so we
look at it as
if this is the lunch you fed them even though that was
a choice that they made.
And therefore you did the transgression of
feeding them שמיטה, Shemitah, of feeding them אינו מעושר. eino me'usar.
Or that's why the יין נסך yayin nesech is an issue even
if it's a non-Jew.
Okay אם עובדי כוכבים הם ונמצא מאכילן יין נסך והרי מזונותם עליו
ונהנה מיין
נסך.
im ovdei kochavim heim venimtza ma'achilan yayin nesech veharei mezonosom alav v'neheneh
miyayin nesech.
Since I have
a legal obligation to provide them lunch
and I am
giving them יין נסך yayin nesech if we look at it that
way, I am satisfying my legal my financial obligation to them with
יין נסך, yayin nesech, I'm getting הנאה hana'ah from יין נסך. yayin
nesech. So that would be if I bought this stuff first and
fed it to them, that would be that problem. But that's not
what happened. I actually gave them the money and they just used
the money as they would use it. So we don't reframe it
as
if I am giving them this food. What? If there's only one
bar in town then it's probable then that might be but again
as most you could discuss is a type of לפני עיוור lifnei
iver and even there not you know it's just funds are fungible.
But the point is that we don't look at it as if
I pay the bill after the fact, we don't look at it
as if I fed them that food. Now wait wait let's keep
on going. עלמא almah so now how's this relevant to the Jaffa
oranges case? עלמא כי פרע דמי איסור כפרע. almah ki para d'mei
issur kapara. I'm sorry I skipped a line. That you can't that
you're allowed to say. ואם אמר להם, ve'im amar lahem, second line
from the top, if he said to them, צאו ואכלו ואני פורע,
tze'u v'ichlu va'ani pore'ah, he didn't say here's the money first. He
said like my example about walking the guy into the McDonald's and
he orders and then you pay his bill, go and eat and
I will pay. Okay צאו ושתו ואני פורע. tze'u ush'u va'ani pore'ah.
I actually had somebody ask me a similar question like you know
somebody who works in a restaurant and my employer was the chef's
birthday and they took him out my employees took him out to
a restaurant, men and take a chef out. To a restaurant and
whatever, anyway, anyway, and it was of course a טרייף treif restaurant
and the chef is Jewish or whatever and now you know like
I'm the employer and I, you know, so I'd like, I want
now to pay for actually part of the cost. Okay, so but
that was again like it was after the fact, but you know,
so if he says go and eat and I'll pay the bill,
okay, then it says חושש משום שביעית משום מעשר משום יין נסך.
Choshesh mishum shevi'is mishum ma'aser mishum yayin nesech. Then since you agreed
to pay the bill from the outset and you paid the bill
at the end, it's like you actually fed them that food. Okay,
and if that's true, so that should be true by the אתנן.
esnan. You said you'd give the sheep at the beginning, you gave
it at the end, okay, so that should sort of, the fact
that it was payment for that thing, okay, makes it like, you
know, gives it that status. אלמא כי פרע, Alma ki para, when
you pay off, you didn't just סתם stam give the money and
they made a choice, so דמי איסורא קפרע, demei issura kapara, so
you're paying, you know, actually something, you know, you're when it's like
you actually are have given them, you know, it gets the status
of that object itself. So we just give them the voucher in
advance is what you're saying? Exactly. So הכא נמי, hacha nami, but
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara concludes with this, הכא נמי, hacha
nami, here too, כי פרע דמי איסורא קפרע. ki para demei issura
kapara. Here too it should be by the אתנן esnan or actually
maybe it's probably going straight to the Jaffa Oranges case, right, it
should be like, you know, it should be considered like the thing
itself when you give back the oranges after the שמיטה shemittah year,
it should be like now just because there's something about איסור issur
doesn't mean it's the same with קדושת שביעית, kedushas shevi'is, okay, but
anyway, but the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying like so what,
at the end of the day you just paid money, you didn't
feed them the food, but we treat it as if the payment
of the money ultimately makes it, it gives it like the same
status of the food. So here too let's say the same thing,
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So תרגמה רב חסדא
בחנוני המקיפו דמשתעבד ליה. Targema Rav Chisda be-chanvani ha-makifo dimishtabed lei. No,
no, no, normally this wouldn't be a problem. It's like at the
end of the day you're just paying off the bill, like the
אתנן esnan at the end of the day you're just paying the
bill, it doesn't get the status of the earlier interaction. Okay, so
then why is it a problem? Because the particular case was that
the store when you said go buy and I'll pay it off,
you sent them to a storekeeper who normally you know and who
normally lets you buy on credit. Okay, why is that relevant? Okay,
דמשתעבד ליה, dimishtabed lei, because then as soon as he pays, as
he gives them the food, you become obligated in the money to
him. What so, דכיון דאורחיה לאקפויי קני ליה דינר גביה. dikivan de-orchai
leakfeyi kanei lei dinar gabei. As soon as he basically gives them
the יין נסך yayin nesech or gives them the אינו מעושר aino
me'ushar or whatever he gives them, okay, it's like because you have
an ongoing relationship with him, it's like he owned the hundred dollars
in your pocket that you were going to pay now, and therefore
meaning conceptually what it is is that we don't just say you
first bought it, then I get a bill, then I pay the
bill, they're separate acts. Okay, if you said that, then fine, the
bill is separate. That's similar to the money given to the to
the prostitute that's not an אתנן, esnan, similar to the Jaffa oranges
they don't have the קדושה, kedusha, it's a separate thing. But the
problem is when it's at the same time. So if Michael here's
the storekeeper, if he paid them and then and then he sent
me a bill, I'm just paying him his bill. It's not like
I fed them that food. It's not like I used יין נסך
yayin nesech to feed my workers. Okay, but if at the moment
he gives it to them I had handed him the money, so
then it's sort of like I got the יין נסך yayin nesech
from him and fed my workers. So since we have an ongoing
relationship, the גמרא Gemara is saying it's not exactly clear at the
end of the day I owe him the money, it's not like
he has the money in my pocket, but it's conceptually like I
paid him at that moment and since it's like I paid him
at that moment, so it's not a separate thing, it's not a
bill that came later. I paid him at the moment, it's like
I bought that food and fed that food to my workers. Okay,
so that's the גמרא, Gemara, we'll see if the גמרא Gemara sticks
with this. חנוני Chanvani is also סתם stam in שביעית. shevi'is. Okay,
that's true. All right, so it says so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אבל חנוני שאין מקיפו מאי, aval chanvani she-ein makifo mai,
but one minute, if it's not a case where like you have
a normal relationship with that storekeeper, what's the story? מותר, mutar, it'll
be permissible because then it's just like the bill comes later. אי
הכי עד דתני צאו ואכלו בדינר זה צאו ושתו בדינר זה, ei
hachi ad de-tani tse'u u-ichlu bedinar zeh, tse'u u-shetu bedinar zeh, why
does it give the only permissible case when I give them the
money upfront? ליפלוג וליתני בדידי, liflog u-lisni bididi, why not split the
case even within when I paid later? במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim
amurim, when is it a problem pay, you know, if they get
fed and then I pay the bill? בחנוני המקיפו, be-chanvani ha-makifo, when
there's like a running tab, דמשתעבד ליה, dimishtabed lei, because then it's
like as soon as he gives them the food, it's like I've
paid him the money. I don't exactly get why the running tab
makes it like that but fine. אבל חנוני שאין מקיפו, aval chanvani
she-ein makifo, but if I don't have a running tab, מותר, mutar,
then why say that's a bigger חידוש, chidush, that in that case
it's permissible because then the bill just comes later and it separates
the two acts. ועוד, ve-ode, and in addition, חנוני שאין מקיפו מי
לא משתעבד. chanvani she-ein makifo mi lo mishtabed. What do you mean?
Like oh you only owe, you know, you owe the money if
it's a guy you have a running tab with. You always owe
the money. The storekeeper pays and now you've agreed to pay the
storekeeper's bill, so you owe him the money regardless. והאמר רבא Veha'amar
Rava האומר לחבירו תן מנה לפלוני ויקנו כל נכסי לך, ha'omer lechaveiro
tein maneh leploni veyiknu kol nechasai lach, if I say to Michael,
Michael, go ahead and you know and give Charlie who's not here,
go ahead and give him a hundred dollars. You want to buy
my field, okay, for a hundred dollars, okay, and קרקע karka is
taken possession with money. So don't give that hundred dollars to me,
give it to Charlie. Okay, and through that act of you giving
it to Charlie, I will treat it as if you paid me
because you're doing it on my behalf, so since you're giving to
Charlie on my behalf it's like I received the money. And therefore
you'll own my field. ויקנו כל נכסי לך Veyiknu kol nechasai lach
קנה. kana.
So then Michael owns my field מדין ערב. midin areiv. It's like
a co-signer.
Like if I say to Michael, lend Charlie a hundred dollars and
I'll
be a co-signer, since he gave Charlie that
money at my behest it's like I borrowed the money. And therefore
Michael can come and collect from me. So when he gives Charlie
the money at my behest it's like I received the money and
it can be a transaction and he owns the field. So how
is this relevant? Because if Michael here now gives my workers the
יין נסך yayin nesech or the אינם מעושרים, einam me'usarim, I don't
know what he's doing with business with יין נסך yayin nesech but
we won't worry about that right now. Anyway, he gives that to
my workers. At that moment he's giving it to them on my
behalf, I owe him the money. Okay, so the Gemara says you
always owe him the money. That's the arrangement. Okay, you said have
the guy send me the bill, so I owe him the money.
So how can you say, so then it should be like an
exchange was done at the time and it should be like I'm
feeding my workers that טריפה treifa food. Now you see why it's
like that case of walking the guy into the McDonald's and he
buys a cheeseburger. Right, even if I say oh you get the
cheeseburger I'll pay the bill after, no, if it's like I'm the
one who's taking responsibility for the bill, right, then it's like I
fed him the cheeseburger. All right, so that seems to be this
case. All right, so let's take a look. אלא אמר רבא Ella
amar Rava לא שנא מקיפו ולא שנא שאינו מקיפו. lo shena makifo
velo shena she'eino makifo. You know what, you're right. It doesn't matter
running bill or not a running bill. Either way it's not a
problem. All of this is to defend the whole Jaffa oranges case
and the אתנן esnan case. אף על גב דמשתעבד ליה, Af al
gav demishtabeid lei, yes, you owe Michael the money, there's a bill
now because he gave it to your, he fed your workers. כיון
דלא מיחד שיבודיה, Keivan delo miyached shibudei, he doesn't own a particular
hundred dollars in my pocket. I just owe him a hundred dollars,
right? So similar to the אתנן, esnan, like you don't say which
sheep. There's not
a particular concrete thing, it's just an outstanding debt I have to
Michael. לא מיצר. lo mitzar. So you know it doesn't become forbidden
like in the, it would like in the אתנן esnan case. If
you don't have a particular sheep, it's just an outstanding debt, then
the money paid afterwards is not related to that transaction. Okay, and
the אתנן esnan given after, the sheep given afterwards is not identified
by that transaction, it's a separate transaction, this just a debt now.
Okay, so and similarly the Jaffa oranges paid later are not in
exchange for פירות שביעית. peiros shevi'is. Okay, they're just a debt. So
paying for the poor person's cheeseburger would be okay because it's just
a debt. It's just a debt, okay? It's not like here is
this for the cheeseburger. Why it's being paid is past history. Right
now it's just a debt, right? Same with the prostitute. Why you
owe this woman a hundred dollars, past history. Right now you just
owe her a hundred dollars. Why you owe these עניים aniyim a
hundred crates of oranges doesn't bother us. Right now it's just a
debt. So it wouldn't even be a problem if I say go
in there and buy a cheeseburger as long as I don't say
buy that cheeseburger? I wouldn't say directly tell them to go ahead,
I mean I have to sort of think about that. They're going
to McDonald's, go in and buy anything from McDonald's. Buy anything from
McDonald's and I'll pay for it, yeah. You could do that, yeah,
even though they're selling בשר בחלב basar bechalav and נבילות neveilos and
whatever, yeah. I mean if they're only selling that I wouldn't do
it. But anyway, but if they could get the salad. Exactly. Okay,
so now the Gemara says like this, okay, where were we? Okay
so אלא הכא מאי חושש משום שביעית ella hacha mai choshesh mishum
shevi'is הא לא מיחד שיבודיה? ha lo miyached shibudei? That was the
question on top because we had on top that you חושש משום
שביעית, choshesh mishum shevi'is, so then you're saying why are we? Oh
oh right, okay, so if in general thank you, so if in
general it's always okay because it's always just a later debt to
be paid, so what is the case that it's a problem? Right,
thank you. הא לא מיחד שיבודיה. Ha lo miyached shibudei. אמר רב
פפא Amar Rav Pappa כגון דאקדים ליה דינר. kegon de'akdim lei dinar.
Ah, the case is, of course it doesn't fit the language because
the language is ואני פורע, Va'ani poreia, I'll pay the bill. But
the way the Gemara is getting out is the only problem is
I first pay Michael. Michael, here's a hundred dollars, pay my workers
based on that whatever they ask for. So when they come in
and ask for אינם מעושרים einam me'usarim or they ask for יין
נסך yayin nesech and I've already paid Michael, then essentially he's giving
them produce that I've paid for. It's like I'm feeding them that
produce. Okay, so אמר רב פפא. amar Rav Pappa. Rav Kahana, so
רב כהנא Rav Kahana said אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, so
רב כהנא Rav Kahana said רמיסי לשמעתי Ramisei lishmahti קמיה דרב זביד
Kamey d'Rav Zvid מנהרדעא. min Naharda. אמר לי אי הכי, Amar li
i hachi, one minute, if that's true, אדתניא Ada tanya צאו ואכלו
צאו ושתו Tzu v'ichlu tzu v'shutu ואני פורע. V'ani poreia. It shouldn't
say go out and eat and drink and I'll pay the bill.
It should say צאו ואכלו צאו ושתו ואני מחשב, Tzu v'ichlu tzu
v'shutu v'ani m'chashev, go out and eat and drink and I'll figure
out the account with the storekeeper afterwards because I've already pre-paid him.
ואני פורע V'ani poreia means I haven't paid him anything yet. מבעי
ליה, Mibaya lei, it should say. אמר ליה, Amar lei, fine, תני
צאו ואני מחשב, Tani tzu v'ani m'chashev, switch the text. Okay, we're
going through a lot of hoops in order to make this ruling
of the Jaffa Oranges okay, but I got to tell you, it's
very helpful because it deals with the cases like I was talking
about. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi amar כגון שנטל ונתן ביד. Kigon
shenatal v'natan b'yad. Okay, ah, no, the case of I will pay
actually means, and this is even a harder read in the ברייתא,
Braita, I go over to Michael and say, Michael, give my workers
it, and Michael says, here, Dov, you're paying the bill, I'm giving
it to you. So he gives it to me and then I
hand it over to the workers. It's like, that's obviously a problem,
right? That's not the case of ואני פורע, V'ani poreia, that's the
case I directly fed it to the workers. So it says, אמר
ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Yeimar l'Rav Ashi, אי
הכי, i hachi, if that's true, אדתניא Ada tanya צאו ואכלו Tzu
v'ichlu צאו ושתו Tzu v'shutu and then ואני פורע, V'ani poreia, what
do you mean go out and eat and drink? תלו ואכלו תלו
ושתו Tlu v'ichlu tlu v'shutu מבעי ליה. Mibaya lei. It should have
been here, here's the food, right? It's not go out and buy
it. It's like if your case is that you're handing them the
food. So you got a problem. You want to say that it
is like never a problem when the bill comes later. But the
ברייתא Braita sounds like it is a problem. ואני פורע. V'ani poreia.
So what's the case of the ברייתא Braita that fits into the
language, that fits into the language? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
no, we're going to just edit the text. תני תלו ואכלו תלו
ושתו. Tani tlu v'ichlu tlu v'shutu. The case is Michael gave me
the food and I hand it to them and I pay up
Michael later, so I guess ואני פורע V'ani poreia works, I haven't
paid Michael yet, Michael's giving it to me on credit and I'm
handing it to them, but the problem is that I'm directly handing
it to them. Okay, so you get the idea. We're basically saying
whether the Jaffa Oranges or the אתנן Esnan or the McDonald's, if
the transaction takes place and then the bill gets sent to me,
that's fine. At that stage, it's just money owed and outstanding debt.
It's not like I'm directly engaged in the transaction. For me to
be directly engaged in the transaction, the money has to be given
and paid at that time and we're just somehow going to squeeze
that in, ignore the Jaffa Oranges pun, squeeze that into the ברייתא
Braita that we just read. Or let's say you called it in,
right? The order of cheeseburgers from McDonald's and paid it later. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. That's the תלו tlu case. Right. Even if you don't
actually physically give it to them, you call it in, someone else
picked it up. Yeah, I assume that'd be the case. Yeah, it's
not physically picking it up. Okay, so let's just read, so that
is really the end of that סוגיא Sugya and like I said,
that has big implications for these types of scenarios that I've given
you. So now we're going to switch gears and we'll just start
with the beginning just to get to the bottom of the דף.
daf. We'll just go one more minute. It says like this, okay,
יתיב רב נחמן ועולא ואבימי בר פפא ויתיב רב חייא בר אמי
גבייהו, Yativ Rav Nachman v'Ulla v'Avimi bar Pappa v'yativ Rav Chiya bar
Ami gaba'aihu, so רב חייא בר אמי Rav Chiya bar Ami was
sitting with them, יתבי וקמיבעיא להו Yatvi v'kamibaya lehu and they raised
the following question: שכרו לשבור ביין נסך מהו? Schoro lishbor b'yayin nesech
mahu? Let's say they hired somebody not to transfer the barrels of
the יין נסך yayin nesech to the truck or anything like that,
but they hired him to do was to break the barrels after
they were done with. Okay. So now what should be the problem?
You're not actually doing anything that helps the יין נסך, yayin nesech,
you know, it's just, I mean barrels that had been used for
יין נסך, yayin nesech, but it should now not be a problem
of משתכר באיסורי הנאה. Mishtaker b'issurei hana'ah. מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say, כיון דרוצה בקיומו אסור? Keivan d'rotzeh b'kiyumo assur? No, because
you want the barrels around until it's time to break them so
that you can so that you can get paid, so that you
have a job to do. You want your חמץ chometz around to
burn it, you don't want it to disappear. Exactly. Right. It's a
little funny question. אודלמא כל אמוטי טיפלא שפיר דמי, O dilma kol
imutei tifla shapir dami, do we say anything that helps get rid
of the טיפלא, tifla, like of the, you know, disgusting thing? I
know that's not an accurate translation of טיפלא, tifla, the, anyway, but
you know, the repugnant thing, that's good. So this is part of
destroying it, so we should say that's not a problem of משתכר
באיסורי הנאה. Mishtaker b'issurei hana'ah. אמר רב נחמן ישבור ותבא עליו ברכה.
Amar Rav Nachman yishbor v'tavo alav bracha. Yeah, let him break it
and he should be blessed. He's part of destroying things related to
יין נסך. yayin nesech. We don't try to make that a technical
problem. Okay, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow.